<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">TRACY, Calif.— The people behind the newest industries in technology are meeting the world's oldest — farming.</s>
    <s id="1:2">Investors and entrepreneurs are putting their money and technology talents into farming and they have an ambitious agenda: to make sure there is enough food for the 10 billion people expected to inhabit the planet by 2100, do it without destroying the world — and make a load of cash along the way.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Silicon Valley is pushing its way into every stage of the food-growing process.</s>
    <s id="2:2">There are tech tycoons buying up farmland, new startup companies selling robots that work the fields, and "hackathon" competitions dedicated to building the next farming app.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">## "Let's Change It"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">"The food sector is wasteful and inefficient," said Ali Partovi, a San Francisco Bay Area investor with large stakes in sustainable agriculture startups.</s>
    <s id="4:2">"Silicon Valley has a hubris that says, 'That's stupid.</s>
    <s id="4:3">Let's change it.'"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">The so-called "ag-tech" sector has seen booming activity.</s>
    <s id="5:2">The sector's growth is measured in the number of new startups, as well as investments by venture capital companies into those startups during their early stages.</s>
    <s id="5:3">Experts predict that ag-tech's growth will outpace today's hottest technologies in another five years or so.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">In the third quarter of this year, venture capitalists and private equity firms invested $269 million into 41 deals in agriculture and food startups.</s>
    <s id="6:2">It was the highest dollar amount ever in that sector and double the amount invested during the same period last year, according to data from Cleantech Group.</s>
    <s id="6:3">Since 2009, investments into this sector have grown an average 63 percent every year.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">"It's going to be bigger than cloud software, it's going to be bigger than Big Data, because everybody eats," said Paul Matteucci, founder of Feeding 10 Billion, a nonprofit center to help ag-tech entrepreneurs.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Dozens of companies are creating technology to make farmland more productive and farming more efficient.</s>
    <s id="8:2">They have designed robots to trim lettuce and software to calculate grass production for cattle grazing.</s>
    <s id="8:3">Others are tapping technology to find substitutes for meat, cheese and eggs.</s>
    <s id="8:4">These fake animal products will mean less land is used to raise livestock, fewer trucks emitting greenhouse gases, and fewer animals subject to inhumane slaughter.</s>
    <s id="8:5">Venture capitalists have propped up startups such as Hampton Creek, which sells mayonnaise and cookies that use plant products instead of eggs.</s>
    <s id="8:6">Another company, Impossible Foods, makes hamburgers and cheese without meat or dairy products.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Silicon Valley isn't just making technology for farms.</s>
    <s id="9:2">Some of its highest-profile investors are buying farmland.</s>
    <s id="9:3">They want to affect how farmers work their fields and influence the type of food that's available for future generations.</s>
    <s id="9:4">Farmland LP buys farms and converts them into organic pastures that crop farmers and cattle and sheep ranchers can share.</s>
    <s id="9:5">The company has attracted some of Silicon Valley's wealthiest investors.</s>
    <s id="9:6">But the draw is more than a happy vision of free-roaming cows.</s>
    <s id="9:7">Many investors see farmland as a safe investment to balance their risky tech investments.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">## Tech-Minded Farmers</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Farmers, for the most part, have welcomed Silicon Valley techies into their world of planting seasons and water woes.</s>
    <s id="11:2">From Salinas to Fresno to Tracy, California farmers are increasingly tech-minded.</s>
    <s id="11:3">They are running their fields from iPads and tracking soil moisture and nitrogen levels with cloud software programs.</s>
    <s id="11:4">Farmers are hungry for more tech solutions that will increase their land's productivity and the money in their bank accounts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">"There is a kind of renaissance in technology in agriculture right now," said Ryan Jacobsen, a farmer and executive director of the Fresno County Farm Bureau.</s>
    <s id="12:2">"It's an exciting time to be a farmer right now."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">In many ways, agriculture is an industry ripe for Silicon Valley — farms were historically on the forefront of manufacturing innovation, and farmers have long embraced new technology.</s>
    <s id="13:2">But farmers and tech startups live in separate worlds.</s>
    <s id="13:3">Only recently have they seen each other as a benefit.</s>
    <s id="13:4">They came together through a number of economic, tech and social factors.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">During the recession, California agriculture remained one of the only bright spots in the state's floundering economy.</s>
    <s id="14:2">While housing prices tanked, farmland value increased — and investors noticed.</s>
    <s id="14:3">There was heightened attention to the state's three-year drought, climate change and the world's swelling population.</s>
    <s id="14:4">The prospect of food shortages became a more immediate problem, grabbing the attention of entrepreneurs who want to build something other than yet another social media app.</s>
    <s id="14:5">Meanwhile, technology got cheaper so more small- and medium-size farmers could buy it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">It became clear that farmers and tech startups could serve each other well.</s>
    <s id="15:2">Blue River Technology in Sunnyvale has created a machine for farmers.</s>
    <s id="15:3">According to Jorge Heraud, the CEO and co-founder of the company, the machine uses digital imaging and powerful software to trim lettuce 100 times faster than people.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">## Costs Vs. Benefits</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Because these machines have replaced human labor, some workers will have to find new jobs.</s>
    <s id="17:2">That's one of the pitfalls — as more technology is introduced to farming, jobs will be cut.</s>
    <s id="17:3">It could discourage immigration to places like the Central Valley, which makes much of the nation's food on the backs of migrant workers and has already seen a labor shortage due to U.S. economic problems and the crackdown on undocumented workers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">"The task of automation has always been about doing the jobs that humans do," Heraud said.</s>
    <s id="18:2">"There will be jobs cost (but) society generally benefits when productivity is increased."</s>
  </p>
</text>
