<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">SEATTLE — Steve Osmek is a wildlife biologist.</s>
    <s id="1:2">He studies living things.</s>
    <s id="1:3">He works at the Seattle-Tacoma Airport.</s>
    <s id="1:4">It's his job to make sure animals play nice with planes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">He's responsible for everything that moves and has legs.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Sometimes, he just needs a fence to keep them out.</s>
    <s id="3:2">There's a tall fence around the airport.</s>
    <s id="3:3">It keeps coyotes and deer away from the runways.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">But it gets more complicated with birds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">## Short Grass, Few Plants With Berries</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">When birds hit planes, it costs airlines lots of money.</s>
    <s id="6:2">It can hurt people, too.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">You can't fence birds out.</s>
    <s id="7:2">So Osmek tries other things.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Osmek has to think about plants.</s>
    <s id="8:2">The grass is cut short.</s>
    <s id="8:3">That way, rats and bugs that birds eat will stay away.</s>
    <s id="8:4">Plants with berries, nuts and seeds are few.</s>
    <s id="8:5">Birds like to eat those plants.</s>
    <s id="8:6">The airport plants shrubs to keep birds from nesting.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Sea-Tac was the first airport to hire a wildlife biologist.</s>
    <s id="9:2">A few others now have the biologists, too.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">Airports are working harder to keep birds away.</s>
    <s id="10:2">It seems to be working.</s>
    <s id="10:3">There are more planes and animals around.</s>
    <s id="10:4">But there are fewer accidents.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">## Bird Radar And Traps</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Osmek traps and moves many birds.</s>
    <s id="12:2">His team tags them and takes them away.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Some birds are killed.</s>
    <s id="13:2">Their bodies go to the Burke Museum for classes to study.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">Seattle is the first airport with bird radar.</s>
    <s id="14:2">The system is better now than when it started.</s>
    <s id="14:3">Airport workers would answer any time a bird showed up.</s>
    <s id="14:4">But by the time they got there, the bird would be gone.</s>
    <s id="14:5">Now they know to look only for flocks.</s>
    <s id="14:6">When they find them, they scare them away with loud noises.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">There's no way for an airport to be perfectly friendly to nature.</s>
    <s id="15:2">People are mixing with wildlife.</s>
    <s id="15:3">But the wildlife was there first.</s>
    <s id="15:4">People can play by nature's rules, and not fight.</s>
    <s id="15:5">And that's why even airports need a wildlife biologist.</s>
  </p>
</text>
