<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">LONDON — When people use their phones to play a game, find the location of something, or post a photo, they may be watched.</s>
    <s id="1:2">Documents leaked by former NSA contractor Edward Snowden suggest that spy agencies can collect personal information from apps on smartphones across the globe.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">The documents were published Monday by The New York Times, the Guardian, and ProPublica.</s>
    <s id="2:2">Mapping, gaming, and social networking apps are common on the world's estimated 1 billion smartphones.</s>
    <s id="2:3">The documents suggest that these apps can feed America's National Security Agency (NSA) and Britain's GCHQ spy agency with huge amounts of personal information.</s>
    <s id="2:4">Location information and details such as a person's political or sexual interests can all be discovered.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">The size of the program isn't known.</s>
    <s id="3:2">Yet, the reports suggest that U.S. and British intelligence can easily get hold of information from apps such as the "Angry Birds" game or Google Maps.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">A 2008 document from the GCHQ describes its joint spying program with the NSA.</s>
    <s id="4:2">It's quoted as saying that the program "effectively means that anyone using Google Maps on a smartphone is working in support of a GCHQ system."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">## Software Used For Spying</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">The NSA did not directly comment on the reports.</s>
    <s id="6:2">But in a statement Monday it claimed that it was only interested in communications of solid "foreign intelligence targets."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">The agency says that it monitors phones for good reason.</s>
    <s id="7:2">Often, they are used in planning terror attacks.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">"Any implication that NSA's foreign intelligence collection is focused on the smartphone or social media communications of everyday Americans is not true," the statement said.</s>
    <s id="8:2">"We collect only those communications that we are authorized by law to collect."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">GCHQ said it did not comment on intelligence matters.</s>
    <s id="9:2">It insisted, however, that all of its activity was "authorized, necessary and proportionate."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">Intelligence agencies' interest in mobile phones and the networks they run on has been documented in several of Snowden's previous leaks.</s>
    <s id="10:2">The focus on apps, however, is new.</s>
    <s id="10:3">It shows how even harmless-looking pieces of software can be used for spying.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">"Angry Birds" was one of the most eye-catching examples.</s>
    <s id="11:2">The addictive birds-versus-pigs game has been downloaded more than 1.7 billion times worldwide.</s>
    <s id="11:3">The Times and ProPublica said a 2012 British intelligence report laid out how to gather "Angry Birds" users' information from phones.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Another document published to the Web was a 14-page-long NSA slideshow.</s>
    <s id="12:2">It listed a host of other mobile apps.</s>
    <s id="12:3">Ones made by social media company Facebook, photo sharing site Flickr, and the film-oriented Flixster were being monitored.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">## Gold Mines Of User Info</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">It wasn't clear precisely what information can be collected from which apps.</s>
    <s id="14:2">One of the slides gave the example of a user who uploaded a photo using a social media app.</s>
    <s id="14:3">Under the words "Golden Nugget!" it said that the information generated by the app could be examined.</s>
    <s id="14:4">A phone's settings, where it connected to, which websites it had visited, which documents it had downloaded, and who its users' friends were could all be found.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Google did not immediately return messages seeking comment on the reports.</s>
    <s id="15:2">Neither did Rovio Entertainment, the maker of "Angry Birds."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">The Times briefly posted a secret U.S. document on the smartphone spying to the web Monday.</s>
    <s id="16:2">It contained material that appeared to publish the name of an NSA employee.</s>
    <s id="16:3">Computer experts said they were able to discover the name of the employee.</s>
    <s id="16:4">They also picked out the name of a Middle Eastern terror group the program was targeting.</s>
    <s id="16:5">Details about the types of computer files the NSA considered useful were also found.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Snowden began leaking documents in June.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Since then, his supporters have maintained they have been careful not to release any intelligence official's name.</s>
    <s id="17:3">They claim to have kept quiet any operational details that could compromise ongoing spying.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">The employee did not return phone or email messages from The Associated Press.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Michael Birmingham is a spokesman for the Director of National Intelligence.</s>
    <s id="19:2">The DNI is in charge of all U.S. spy agencies — including the NSA, CIA and FBI — and reports to the president.</s>
    <s id="19:3">Birmingham said the agency requested the Times not publish the information.</s>
    <s id="19:4">A Times spokeswoman said the information had been posted by error.</s>
    <s id="19:5">The material has since been removed.</s>
  </p>
</text>
