<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla.</s>
    <s id="1:2">— Science teacher Stephen Kajiura and three of his students were on a boat out in the ocean.</s>
    <s id="1:3">They were hoping to catch sharks.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Thousands of blacktip sharks come to South Florida every winter.</s>
    <s id="2:2">The animals travel from up north looking for warmer waters.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Kajiura has been catching some of these sharks.</s>
    <s id="3:2">He is putting transmitters inside their bodies.</s>
    <s id="3:3">A transmitter is a small machine that gives off sounds or other kinds of signals.</s>
    <s id="3:4">Such signals allow scientists to track a transmitter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Once Kajiura has put a transmitter in a shark, he sets the animal free.</s>
    <s id="4:2">Scientists can then track where the shark is going.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">The sharks come from as far away as North Carolina each year.</s>
    <s id="5:2">They spend the winter in South Florida's warm waters.</s>
    <s id="5:3">Then, they head back up north.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">## Bites Rarely Harm Humans Badly</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">Blacktip sharks typically grow to be 5 or 6 feet long.</s>
    <s id="7:2">They sometimes bite people.</s>
    <s id="7:3">These attacks usually are not that serious, however.</s>
    <s id="7:4">The sharks sometimes grab a human hand or foot.</s>
    <s id="7:5">Once they realize they have not caught a fish, they usually let go right away.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Last year, two people in South Florida were bitten by blacktip sharks: a man and a 9-year-old boy.</s>
    <s id="8:2">Neither was badly harmed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Kajiura said it is important to understand just where the sharks are going.</s>
    <s id="9:2">It is also important to understand if they are changing where they go.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">## Sharks Help Keep Ocean Life In Balance</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Sharks are good for South Florida's ocean waters, Kaijura said.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Sharks eat a lot of fish.</s>
    <s id="11:3">They help keep ocean life in balance.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">There could be problems if the sharks stop coming.</s>
    <s id="12:2">South Florida might end up with too many of certain kinds of fish.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Those fish eat other, smaller fish.</s>
    <s id="13:2">Soon, there could be too few of the smaller fish.</s>
    <s id="13:3">The smaller fish eat plants.</s>
    <s id="13:4">Without enough of them, certain plants would become overgrown.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">Since 2011, Kajiura has been studying where sharks go during the winter.</s>
    <s id="14:2">He said they look for places that are just warm enough for them to be comfortable.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">South Florida might not be their favorite winter spot for too much longer, though.</s>
    <s id="15:2">Temperatures around the world are rising.</s>
    <s id="15:3">Scientists say this is because of pollution.</s>
    <s id="15:4">The rise in temperatures is known as global warming.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">## Warmer Water Might Change Shark Habits</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Kajiura said blacktip sharks might change their habits as temperatures get warmer.</s>
    <s id="17:2">The animals could start to spend their winters further north.</s>
    <s id="17:3">They might no longer come down as far as South Florida.</s>
    <s id="17:4">Then, certain kinds of fish could become too common.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">On a Tuesday morning, Kajiura and his crew set out to catch a few sharks.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">The team laid out 60 hooks.</s>
    <s id="19:2">All were attached to a floating line.</s>
    <s id="19:3">The scientists put hunks of mackerel and fish heads on the hooks so the sharks would bite them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">The team caught two sharks.</s>
    <s id="20:2">Then things started to go wrong.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">One shark escaped before they could put a transmitter in it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">They did manage to get a transmitter into the other shark.</s>
    <s id="22:2">However, it died almost immediately.</s>
    <s id="22:3">It was too upset about being caught.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">"That's very rare," Kajiura said.</s>
    <s id="23:2">Usually, "the sharks get away just fine.</s>
    <s id="23:3">We've only lost a couple of animals ever."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">## High-Pitched Pings Help Track Sharks</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">Kajiura has put transmitters into about a dozen sharks since December.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">The transmitters give off pinging sounds.</s>
    <s id="26:2">These pings are so high-pitched they cannot be heard by fish or other ocean animals.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">Each transmitter's pings have their own pattern.</s>
    <s id="27:2">Because of this, scientists are able to find each of the sharks.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">"We're interested in what these sharks are doing when they're here," he said.</s>
    <s id="28:2">"Where are they going when they leave?</s>
    <s id="28:3">How far up the coast do they go?"</s>
  </p>
</text>
