<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">ROME — Crews have pulled the cruise ship Costa Concordia from the rocks off the Italian island where it sank.</s>
    <s id="1:2">The shipped had been wrecked upon the rocks for the last 20 months.</s>
    <s id="1:3">It is set to be removed from the shoreline by mid-2014, experts said Tuesday.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">The operation to straighten the 300-meter, 114,000-ton ship took 19 hours.</s>
    <s id="2:2">Engineers had hoped it could be done in 10 to 12 hours.</s>
    <s id="2:3">But getting it right was more important that doing it fast.</s>
    <s id="2:4">The ship is longer than three football fields and weighs more than 28,000 elephants.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">"I am relieved and I am a bit tired.</s>
    <s id="3:2">I will have a beer and go to sleep.</s>
    <s id="3:3">I am sending a kiss to my wife," the South African-born Nick Sloane said as he emerged from the barge from which he commanded the operation.</s>
    <s id="3:4">He is in charge of pulling the wreck out of the sea.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">The body of the ship was lifted using steel cables and tanks.</s>
    <s id="4:2">They were attached to the side that was above water.</s>
    <s id="4:3">The tanks were filled with water.</s>
    <s id="4:4">They weight of the tanks helped pull up the wreck.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">## Next, Refloating The Ship</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">Engineers planned to inspect the muddy brown side that came out of the water.</s>
    <s id="6:2">It was badly misshapen.</s>
    <s id="6:3">The idea is to attach tanks on that side.</s>
    <s id="6:4">Then the tanks will be filled with air to help the ship float again.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">Once it is floating, the Concordia was expected to be towed to a port to be taken apart.</s>
    <s id="7:2">Franco Porcellacchia is an engineer overseeing the operations.</s>
    <s id="7:3">He works for Costa Crociere, the company that owns the ship.</s>
    <s id="7:4">He was sure it could all be done in the first half of next year.</s>
    <s id="7:5">Work cannot be done faster because it is difficult to operate during the winter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Straightening the Concordia was a major engineering project.</s>
    <s id="8:2">The risk was that the rusting hull could snap or sink entirely.</s>
    <s id="8:3">Then the ship could not be saved, or salvaged.</s>
    <s id="8:4">The waters surrounding the wreck could have been badly polluted.</s>
    <s id="8:5">It would have been a disaster.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">"It could not have gone any better," Porcellacchia said.</s>
    <s id="9:2">Italian Civil Protection agency chief Franco Gabrielli attacked people who thought the worst would happen.</s>
    <s id="9:3">Some thought a lot of sewage would have been released from the ship.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">Instead, poisonous liquids were not released.</s>
    <s id="10:2">Fuel was removed from the Concordia two months after its shipwreck.</s>
    <s id="10:3">Still, leftover fuel, chemicals and rotting food were thought to have dirtied the seawater inside the body of the ship.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">## Sirens Blare As Ship Righted</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Salvage team members hugged as the straightening was completed.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Sirens in the port of Giglio blared in celebration.</s>
    <s id="12:3">Giglio is a tiny port city where the Concordia ran aground.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">All those working on the rescue "are a great (source) of Italian pride," Prime Minister Enrico Letta wrote on Twitter.</s>
    <s id="13:2">He invited Gabrielli and others for a meeting in Rome.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">The sinking of the Concordia has been a national shame.</s>
    <s id="14:2">It was blamed on the irresponsible behavior of its Italian captain, Francesco Schettino.</s>
    <s id="14:3">The image of the half-sunken ship was also associated with the state of the country.</s>
    <s id="14:4">Italy has had bad money problems.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Insurers for Costa are paying for the salvage operation, which is the first of its kind.</s>
    <s id="15:2">The cost is estimated at more than $800 million.</s>
    <s id="15:3">More than 500 people from 26 nations are working on salvaging the ship.</s>
    <s id="15:4">Costa is an Italian unit of Carnival, a U.S.-based cruise line company.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">The Concordia crashed against a reef on Jan. 12, 2012.</s>
    <s id="16:2">Thirty-two of the 4,229 people on board died and two victims — an Indian waiter and an Italian passenger — are still missing.</s>
    <s id="16:3">Rescuers were expected to board the vessel to look for their remains.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">## Captain Had Abandoned His Ship</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Schettino is being tried for serious crimes.</s>
    <s id="18:2">He was due to next appear in court on Sept. 23.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">The disgraced captain is accused of having taken the ship dangerously close to the shore to perform a stunt.</s>
    <s id="19:2">He also is accused of badly mishandling the emergency on the night of the disaster.</s>
    <s id="19:3">He left the Concordia before all passengers had been evacuated.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Four other crew members and a Costa Crociere boss were given jail terms ranging from 18 to 34 months.</s>
    <s id="20:2">But they do not have to serve the sentences.</s>
    <s id="20:3">They agreed to admit to their crimes.</s>
    <s id="20:4">Costa Crociere was fined $1.33 million in another plea deal in April.</s>
  </p>
</text>
