<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">LOS ANGELES — On Thursday, California workers poked hollow aluminum tubes into Sierra Nevada meadows to measure the snowpack.</s>
    <s id="1:2">They did not find much.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">"We will conceivably see more years like this in the future," said Jeffrey Mount, a geologist with the Public Policy Institute of California.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">The Earth has been getting warmer, scientists say, and the climate is expected to keep getting warmer.</s>
    <s id="3:2">Many scientists blame humans.</s>
    <s id="3:3">When we burn fossil fuels like gas, oil or coal it releases gasses known as greenhouse gasses.</s>
    <s id="3:4">They get trapped in the atmosphere and heat up the Earth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">## A Dry January</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">Scientists say the state's mountain snowpack could shrink as a result.</s>
    <s id="5:2">The snowpack is the layers of snow that build up over time.</s>
    <s id="5:3">By the end of the century, more than half of the snowpack could disappear.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">But that doesn't mean nature will provide less water to California.</s>
    <s id="6:2">The latest climate studies suggest the overall amount of precipitation won't change much, and may even increase across much of California.</s>
    <s id="6:3">However, more of it will fall as rain and less as snow.</s>
    <s id="6:4">This change will force the state to alter the way it manages one of the world's most complicated water systems.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">On Thursday, the snowpack was just 25 percent of the average for this time of year.</s>
    <s id="7:2">A dry January is partly to blame, and the storms that hit the state in December dumped heavy amounts of rain, not snow.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">At its peak, the California snowpack holds about 15 million acre-feet of water.</s>
    <s id="8:2">That is enough water to fill Shasta Lake, the state's largest reservoir, more than three times.</s>
    <s id="8:3">The snow melts gradually over several months, trickling down mountains into rivers and reservoirs in the spring and early summer.</s>
    <s id="8:4">The reservoirs fill just when the need for drinking water and water to irrigate farmland goes up.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">## Changing Rules For Dams?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">Rain, on the other hand, "has to be dealt with immediately.</s>
    <s id="10:2">You can't wait," said Kelly Redmond, deputy director of the Western Regional Climate Center in Nevada.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Dealing with the heavy rains was not a problem in December.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Because there had been three years of severe drought in the state, the reservoirs had plenty of room to absorb the water.</s>
    <s id="11:3">The level of Shasta Lake rose by nearly 60 feet.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Due to climate change, though, there could soon be more rain in winter than California's water system could handle, said Dan Cayan, a climate scientist at Scripps Institution of Oceanography.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Cayan added that the temperature in California has risen 1-degree Fahrenheit since the 1950s.</s>
    <s id="12:3">Even that single degree increase has already cost California and the West 5 percent to 10 percent of its snowpack.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Adapting to the extra winter rainfall could literally require an act of Congress.</s>
    <s id="13:2">Dams control the flow of water in and out of the reservoirs.</s>
    <s id="13:3">They are operated according to a set of rules developed for each reservoir by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.</s>
    <s id="13:4">Congress has to approve any changes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">The California Department of Water Resources and the federal government together operate most of California's large dams.</s>
    <s id="14:2">They are studying whether the rules should be changed because of the warming climate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">## More Water Storage Needed</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">The state also is considering taking into account weather forecasts.</s>
    <s id="16:2">If heavy rains were headed for the Sierra, for instance, water could be released from the reservoirs to make room.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">None of this is simple.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Letting water out to make room for rain that never comes would mean less water for people.</s>
    <s id="17:3">Yet, filling up reservoirs in the winter may cause flooding during spring storms.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">"Who wants to be the responsible person for not having that flood space in the reservoir?" asked Iris Stewart-Frey, a professor at Santa Clara University who has studied changes in the snowmelt.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Many experts say an obvious solution is to build more water storage.</s>
    <s id="19:2">"I think if you want to replace 5 million acre-feet of lost snowpack, I don't see any other way than more storage," state hydrologist Maury Roos said.</s>
    <s id="19:3">Hydrology is the study of water.</s>
    <s id="19:4">Roos uses science and math to solve water-related problems in the state.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">But should California build new reservoirs or increase groundwater storage, or both?</s>
    <s id="20:2">Groundwater is water located beneath the Earth's surface, so groundwater storage is less likely to evaporate.</s>
    <s id="20:3">Also, who would pay for the costs of the new storage?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">The loss of snowpack is "definitely going to be a problem," said Jay Lund, director of the Center for Watershed Sciences at University of California, Davis.</s>
    <s id="21:2">But if it's managed well, Lund said it should not be a disaster.</s>
  </p>
</text>
