<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">MALAM JABBA, Pakistan — Boys bomb down the powdery slopes of Malam Jabba.</s>
    <s id="1:2">They wear tattered coats and homemade pine skis.</s>
    <s id="1:3">Their ski boots are galoshes nailed to the planks.</s>
    <s id="1:4">Bamboo sticks stand in for ski poles.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Nearby, jobless men climb a snowy ridge.</s>
    <s id="2:2">They are seeking scrap metal in the rubble.</s>
    <s id="2:3">This was once a ski resort  -– the only one in all of Pakistan.</s>
    <s id="2:4">People called it "the Switzerland of Pakistan."</s>
    <s id="2:5">The rich and powerful used to come here to enjoy the rugged peaks.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">## Taliban Terror</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Malam Jabba is in the scenic Swat Valley.</s>
    <s id="4:2">In 2008 Taliban fighters seized the valley.</s>
    <s id="4:3">The Taliban was brutal.</s>
    <s id="4:4">The fighters killed anyone they believed to be their enemy.</s>
    <s id="4:5">They burned down schools and banned girls from attending classes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">The militants said skiing was against their religion.</s>
    <s id="5:2">The resort hotel was set on fire.</s>
    <s id="5:3">They destroyed its chairlift, snow-making machine and ski-rental shops.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">The government regained control of the valley in 2009.</s>
    <s id="6:2">However, Malam Jabba is barely back in business.</s>
    <s id="6:3">It is a symbol of Pakistan's struggle to win back tourism.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">In October, the Taliban tried to kill 15-year-old Malala Yousafzai.</s>
    <s id="7:2">She was targeted because she promotes education for girls.</s>
    <s id="7:3">When Malala was shot, it raised fears that the Taliban would bring more violence to the Swat Valley.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">## Still Waiting For Help</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">"The government has been telling us for years that they're going to rebuild the hotel, and it never happens," said Sabz Ali.</s>
    <s id="9:2">The 18-year-old was climbing up the slope with his skis over his shoulder.</s>
    <s id="9:3">His family owns a small hotel nearby.</s>
    <s id="9:4">The hotel only makes about $20 a month.</s>
    <s id="9:5">"The [big] hotel is the main thing.</s>
    <s id="9:6">If they build it, people will come."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">Pakistan tourism has an image problem.</s>
    <s id="10:2">People are afraid it is just a land of religious extremists and car bombers.</s>
    <s id="10:3">But it is home to the world's second-highest peak, K2.</s>
    <s id="10:4">It has ancient ruins and giant cliff sculptures.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Swat Valley was the crown jewel of Pakistani tourism.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Its velvet-green mountainsides drew visitors.</s>
    <s id="11:3">The winding Swat River has the best trout fishing in the country.</s>
    <s id="11:4">And then there is Malam Jabba, Swat's own little Aspen.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">## Heartbreak Hotel</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">The resort used to host thousands of people each day;</s>
    <s id="13:2">now, the number is usually in the dozens.</s>
    <s id="13:3">The ruined hotel was a striking, white, modern building with a curved roof.</s>
    <s id="13:4">It was different from the typical boxy buildings found in Pakistan.</s>
    <s id="13:5">Inside the lobby were fireplaces, wood panels and dark red carpeting.</s>
    <s id="13:6">Guests could skate on the ice rink after skiing.</s>
    <s id="13:7">A souvenir shop sold jars of honey made in Swat.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">"It was a beautiful, huge hotel, and it was always full," Ali said.</s>
    <s id="14:2">He and his family fled Swat during the fighting.</s>
    <s id="14:3">They returned four months later to find the hotel destroyed.</s>
    <s id="14:4">"When I saw it, my heart sank.</s>
    <s id="14:5">It was so beautiful, but it also meant we had jobs."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">## Tourists Remain Wary</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">The military is still guarding Swat.</s>
    <s id="16:2">Bases and checkpoints ensure that the Taliban doesn't return.</s>
    <s id="16:3">"Swat is now totally cleared of the Taliban," said Syed Aqil Shah, tourism minister for the Swat Valley.</s>
    <s id="16:4">"What happened to Malala was just one incident that made people start talking again about Swat security.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">"But I assure you that Swat is as safe as any other place in Pakistan right now."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Nonetheless, tourism is not what it used to be.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">About 50,000 tourists visit Swat per year, said Zahid Khan.</s>
    <s id="19:2">He is the president of the All-Swat Hotels Association.</s>
    <s id="19:3">Before the Taliban takeover there were 300,000 visitors a year.</s>
    <s id="19:4">Almost everyone in Swat earned a living from tourism.</s>
    <s id="19:5">The drop in visitors has hurt nearly everyone Khan said.</s>
    <s id="19:6">Hotel workers, cooks, taxi drivers and souvenir makers are all losing money.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">According to Khan, nobody in the government is helping.</s>
    <s id="20:2">His requests to meet with top officials get ignored, he said.</s>
    <s id="20:3">So are his pleas for funding.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">## More Bad Luck for Swat</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">Making matters worse, the valley was flooded in 2010.</s>
    <s id="22:2">More than 120 hotels in Swat were damaged or destroyed.</s>
    <s id="22:3">Only 20 have been rebuilt.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">The local government said reconstruction of the hotel should begin this summer.</s>
    <s id="23:2">People in Swat say they have heard such promises before.</s>
    <s id="23:3">They are just scraping by.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">## Skiing Against All Odds</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">The resort still brings some joy to residents.</s>
    <s id="25:2">Skiing is all they have to fill their days.</s>
    <s id="25:3">On a recent cloudless afternoon, a few dozen people spent hours on the mountain doing jumps.</s>
    <s id="25:4">One skier in an overcoat whizzed down without poles.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">"It's such a beautiful sport that I can't help but ski every day," said Saeed Alam, 22.</s>
    <s id="26:2">He pushed off down the slope.</s>
    <s id="26:3">On the back of his jacket were the words "Ski and Smile in Swat!"</s>
  </p>
</text>
