<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">UNITED NATIONS — Caribbean countries were European colonies 200 or more years ago, during the height of the African slave trade.</s>
    <s id="1:2">Now they want money from European countries to make up for the problems caused by slavery.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Those payments are called reparations.</s>
    <s id="2:2">They are meant to repair the damage that the Caribbean countries say continues today.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Almost every Caribbean leader who spoke at the United Nation last week brought up the issue.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">The fight is many years old.</s>
    <s id="4:2">Black scholars and others across the United States, Caribbean and Africa have unsuccessfully sought money from Britain, France and the Netherlands.</s>
    <s id="4:3">But they were never supported by most citizens or political leaders.</s>
    <s id="4:4">Now that has changed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">## Reparations To Fight Poverty</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">The push for reparations has been gaining steam in recent weeks.</s>
    <s id="6:2">Leaders of the 15-member Caribbean Community group agreed to ask the former colonial powers to pay up.</s>
    <s id="6:3">They have met with a British law firm and called for apologies.</s>
    <s id="6:4">They might even go to the International Court of Justice if the Europeans will not deal with them.</s>
    <s id="6:5">The court is the United Nations' main legal arm.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">The leaders say what they want most is money for programs to help lift people out of poverty.</s>
    <s id="7:2">The money could be used for things like building schools and making bridges and roads.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Ralph Gonsalves is prime minister of St. Vincent and the Grenadines.</s>
    <s id="8:2">He is one of the leaders.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">"It's a historic wrong that has to be righted," Gonsalves said.</s>
    <s id="9:2">He noted that other groups have received payments for historic wrongs, especially during World War II.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">"It's not a confrontation, it's a conversation" that the Caribbean nations are seeking for the 400-year-old problem, Gonsalves said.</s>
    <s id="10:2">"It's not a protest.</s>
    <s id="10:3">It's an engagement."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">## European Leaders Resist Reparations</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">It is not clear if other nations will join the Caribbean's call.</s>
    <s id="12:2">On Monday, the U.N. unveiled the winning design of a memorial to honor the victims of slavery.</s>
    <s id="12:3">The memorial will be built at U.N. headquarters.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Gonsalves and other leaders say they welcome the memorial and the U.N.'s efforts.</s>
    <s id="13:2">But more action is needed, he said.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">Leaders of African countries like South Africa, Ghana and Ethiopia are "on board," Gonsalves said.</s>
    <s id="14:2">"We're going to build the links.</s>
    <s id="14:3">We have to build it inside of Europe, too, with ordinary Europeans."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">But European governments might not listen.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">French President François Hollande resists demands from Haiti to pay reparations.</s>
    <s id="16:2">Haiti was a French colony.</s>
    <s id="16:3">His refusal to that country matched that of Jacques Chirac.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">He was the French president when Haiti was celebrating its 200th birthday almost 10 years ago.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Haitian President Jean-Bertrand Aristide demanded that France repay Haiti for the amount it was forced to pay for its freedom in 1804.</s>
    <s id="17:3">Aristide had sent Paris a bill for the amount.</s>
    <s id="17:4">He calculated it down to the last penny: $21,685,135,571.48.</s>
    <s id="17:5">Chirac quickly said no.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Britain also still hasn't apologized for slavery, activists say.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">## It Could Be A Long Fight</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Blacks in America have not succeeded in their efforts, either.</s>
    <s id="20:2">Attempts to have the courts force the U.S. to pay reparations for slavery have gone nowhere.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">Still, Heather Russell says she is "cautiously hopeful" about the Caribbean Community's latest efforts.</s>
    <s id="21:2">The Jamaican native is a professor of Caribbean and African-American literature.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">"You have 15 heads of government who have signed on," said Russell.</s>
    <s id="22:2">"This issue has never been squarely put on the table."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">Verene Shepherd is a historian who has fought a long time for reparations.</s>
    <s id="23:2">She said people are more aware about the effects of slavery today.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">"Remember, slavery lasted 300 to 400 years.</s>
    <s id="24:2">In the scheme of things, we have not been fighting a long time," she said.</s>
  </p>
</text>
