<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">UNITED NATIONS — Caribbean countries face plenty of problems.</s>
    <s id="1:2">There's rising unemployment, high crime and an unending health crisis.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">But almost every Caribbean leader who spoke at the United Nation last week brought up one issue: paying for the damages of slavery.</s>
    <s id="2:2">The countries were European colonies during the African slave trade.</s>
    <s id="2:3">They want money, or reparations, for the descendants of African slaves.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Antigua and Barbuda Prime Minister Baldwin Spencer said the Caribbean countries have had a lot of trouble making their economies better.</s>
    <s id="3:2">The problems continue because of slavery and because they were once colonies.</s>
    <s id="3:3">"Reparations must be directed toward repairing the damage inflicted by slavery and racism."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">The fight is many years old.</s>
    <s id="4:2">Black scholars and others across the United States, Caribbean and Africa have unsuccessfully sought money from Britain, France and the Netherlands.</s>
    <s id="4:3">They want the European countries to pay for supporting kidnapping, enslaving and selling Africans.</s>
    <s id="4:4">But their idea was never backed by most citizens or political leaders.</s>
    <s id="4:5">Now that has changed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">## Caribbean Leaders Band Together</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">The push for reparations has been gaining steam in recent weeks.</s>
    <s id="6:2">Leaders of the 15-member Caribbean Community regional bloc have agreed to make a case for the former colonial powers to pay up.</s>
    <s id="6:3">They have met with a British law firm and called for apologies.</s>
    <s id="6:4">They might even go to the International Court of Justice, the United Nations' main legal arm, if the Europeans will not deal with them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">The leaders say what they most want is money for programs to help lift people out of poverty.</s>
    <s id="7:2">The money could be used for things like building schools and making bridges and roads.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Ralph Gonsalves is prime minister of St. Vincent and the Grenadines.</s>
    <s id="8:2">He is one of the leaders of the movement.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">"It's a historic wrong that has to be righted," Gonsalves said.</s>
    <s id="9:2">"Look, the Germans paid the Jews."</s>
    <s id="9:3">He also noted payments to Japanese people in the United States who were forced into camps during World War II.</s>
    <s id="9:4">The Maori people received reparations from New Zealand, too.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">A group was formed to work on reparations for the Caribbean countries at a meeting Gonsalves hosted.</s>
    <s id="10:2">Hilary Beckles, a leading historian on the issue of slavery and reparations, was selected to lead the group.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Beckles recently published a book.</s>
    <s id="11:2">In it he argues that Britain built its economic empire on slave labor.</s>
    <s id="11:3">The effects of slavery continue to be seen in the problems Caribbean countries have with improving their fortunes, the book said.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">## European Leaders Say No To Reparations</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">"It's not a confrontation, it's a conversation" that the Caribbean nations are seeking for the 400-year-old problem, Gonsalves said.</s>
    <s id="13:2">"It's not a protest.</s>
    <s id="13:3">It's an engagement."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">It is unclear whether other nations will join the Caribbean's call.</s>
    <s id="14:2">On Monday, the U.N. unveiled the winning design of a memorial at U.N. headquarters to honor the victims of slavery.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Gonsalves and other leaders say they welcome the memorial and the U.N.'s efforts.</s>
    <s id="15:2">But more action is needed, he said.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">"I saw the president of South Africa, the president of Ghana, the prime minister of Ethiopia, and they are all on board," Gonsalves said.</s>
    <s id="16:2">"We're going to build the links.</s>
    <s id="16:3">We have to build it inside of Europe, too, with ordinary Europeans."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">But if Europeans are willing to listen, their governments may not be.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">French President François Hollande resists demands to pay reparations for its part in Haiti's independence and the slave trade.</s>
    <s id="18:2">He refused just like Jacques Chirac before him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Chirac was the French president when Haiti was celebrating its 200th birthday almost 10 years ago.</s>
    <s id="19:2">Haitian President Jean-Bertrand Aristide demanded that France repay Haiti for the amount it was forced to pay for its freedom in 1804.</s>
    <s id="19:3">Aristide had sent Paris a bill for the amount, down to the last penny, of $21,685,135,571.48.</s>
    <s id="19:4">Chirac quickly said no.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Britain also still hasn't apologized for slavery, activists say.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">## "Squarely Put On The Table"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">Blacks in America have had no more success than their counterparts.</s>
    <s id="22:2">Attempts to have the courts force the U.S. to pay reparations for slavery have gone nowhere.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">Still, Heather Russell, a professor of Caribbean and African-American literature, says she is "cautiously hopeful" about the Caribbean Community's latest efforts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">"You have 15 heads of government who have signed on," said Russell, a Jamaica native.</s>
    <s id="24:2">"This issue has never been squarely put on the table."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">Verene Shepherd is a historian and who has fought a long time for reparations.</s>
    <s id="25:2">She said people are more aware about the affects of slavery today.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">"Remember, slavery lasted 300 to 400 years.</s>
    <s id="26:2">In the scheme of things, we have not been fighting a long time," she said.</s>
  </p>
</text>
