<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">ISTANBUL — Violence between police and protesters continued this week in Turkey.</s>
    <s id="1:2">Demonstrators against the government have gathered in Istanbul's Taksim Square since May 28.</s>
    <s id="1:3">The police tried to remove them again on Tuesday.</s>
    <s id="1:4">Officers fired tear gas into a group of around 10,000 people.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Four people have been killed since the clashes began.</s>
    <s id="2:2">Doctors believe that nearly 5,000 people have been injured.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">## City On Two Continents</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Istanbul has 13.9 million residents and is one of the largest cities in the world.</s>
    <s id="4:2">It also spreads over two continents.</s>
    <s id="4:3">One half of Istanbul is in Europe while the other half of the city is in Asia.</s>
    <s id="4:4">The city is connected by bridges and ferries across one of the busiest waterways on the planet.</s>
    <s id="4:5">Istanbul plays a major role in global trade and Turkey has long had friendly relations with the U.S.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">Turkey is larger than the state of Texas.</s>
    <s id="5:2">It has borders with Greece in the west and Iran in the east.</s>
    <s id="5:3">Istanbul is a very modern city, but other parts of Turkey are less developed.</s>
    <s id="5:4">Around 99 percent of Turks have a Muslim background.</s>
    <s id="5:5">But religion is officially separated from politics in Turkey.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">Some people feel Turkey's leader, Prime Minister, Recep Tayyip Erdogan, has tried to force religious laws onto the people.</s>
    <s id="6:2">Erdogan's opponents say this is just one reason why they are demonstrating against him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">## Pulling Down A Park For A Shopping Mall</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">The protests started when people discovered that a popular park was going to be paved over.</s>
    <s id="8:2">A shopping center is planned to be built in its place.</s>
    <s id="8:3">Gezi Park is a favorite place for many Turkish people.</s>
    <s id="8:4">A protester held a sign that said:"What if they tried to demolish Central Park in New York to build a mall?</s>
    <s id="8:5">That's happening here."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Riot police violently removed the first protest from the park.</s>
    <s id="9:2">After that, the demonstrations grew much bigger.</s>
    <s id="9:3">The protests are now against the police, against Erdogan, and the government.</s>
    <s id="9:4">The demonstrators are both young and old.</s>
    <s id="9:5">They have lots of different kinds of jobs.</s>
    <s id="9:6">Teachers, lawyers, office workers and students are all protesting together.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">## Violent Removal</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">On Tuesday morning, riot police once again removed people from the park.</s>
    <s id="11:2">They used tear gas, water cannons and armored vehicles.</s>
    <s id="11:3">There were reports that several hundred people were injured.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Several ambulances were seen at the scene.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Online videos showed protesters panicking as they inhaled the tear gas, which makes it hard to breathe.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">## Secret Police Starting A Fight?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">During the removal, some people threw firebombs at the police.</s>
    <s id="14:2">The protesters said they had never seen the bombers before, and others said they saw the bombers carrying walkie-talkies.</s>
    <s id="14:3">Some believe that they were secret policemen who were sent to the park to start a fight and make the protesters look violent.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Police also stormed a courthouse after lawyers protested against Erdogan there.</s>
    <s id="15:2">At least 44 lawyers were arrested.</s>
    <s id="15:3">The President of the Turkish Lawyers' Association, Metin Feyzioglu, told reporters that there were "terrible scenes."</s>
    <s id="15:4">Thousands of lawyers came onto the streets on Wednesday to support their colleagues and protest their treatment.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">Prime Minister Erdogan defended the use of police force against the demonstrators.</s>
    <s id="16:2">He said the police officers had done a good job.</s>
    <s id="16:3">He accused the protesters of committing crimes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">## "What Should We Have Done?"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Erdogan promised to "pursue" the demonstrators who he described as "terrorists."</s>
    <s id="18:2">No one will escape, he also threatened.</s>
    <s id="18:3">"What should we have done?" </s>
    <s id="18:4">the prime minister asked.</s>
    <s id="18:5">"Kneeled down in front of these people and asked them to please remove their banners?"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Erdogan said the protests are organized by a foreign country to damage Turkey economically.</s>
    <s id="19:2">There might be a public vote to decide on the future of the park.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">The U.N. and U.S. government told Turkey to respect the protesters' rights.</s>
    <s id="20:2">Caitlin Hayden is a spokeswoman for the U.S. National Security Council.</s>
    <s id="20:3">Hayden said that she is "concerned by any attempts to punish" people for "exercising their right to free speech."</s>
    <s id="20:4">U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-Moon called for a conversation between the government and the protesters to resolve the dispute.</s>
  </p>
</text>
