<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">SEATTLE — Steve Osmek is standing next to a tangle of shrubs and wildflowers, talking about conservation.</s>
    <s id="1:2">But every 45 seconds or so, a jet rumbles overhead — drowning out all his words.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">He's used to the planes by now.</s>
    <s id="2:2">As the resident wildlife biologist at Seattle-Tacoma International Airport, Osmek is in charge of making sure animals play nice with the planes.</s>
    <s id="2:3">"If it moves, if it has legs, I'm responsible," he says.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Sometimes, it's simply a matter of keeping animals out, like the 12-foot fence that prevents coyotes and deer from wandering onto the runways.</s>
    <s id="3:2">But it's more complicated for the airport's greatest wildlife hazard: birds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Bird strikes cost the U.S. aviation industry $700 million annually, according to the Federal Aviation Administration, and more than 200 people have died as a result of bird-plane collisions in the past quarter-century worldwide.</s>
    <s id="4:2">When a flight taking off from New York's LaGuardia Airport lost engine power after hitting a flock of geese but landed safely in the river in 2009, it was called "Miracle on the Hudson" for good reason.</s>
    <s id="4:3">Sea-Tac had an emergency landing of its own in 2002, when a Boeing 737 struck 26 birds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">There's no barrier to put up against birds.</s>
    <s id="5:2">Instead, Osmek is talking about conservation biology in a grassy field next to Sea-Tac.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">Airports are ecosystems despite all the concrete.</s>
    <s id="6:2">They're home not only to planes and trucks but also pigeons, voles, grasshoppers, blackberry shrubs, and even salmon, in the case of Sea-Tac.</s>
    <s id="6:3">Managing bird strikes is about creating environments that discourage the hazardous birds, especially ones that flock, like European starlings, or large birds of prey, like red-tailed hawks.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">That means Osmek is actually responsible for things that don't move and don't have legs, either;</s>
    <s id="7:2">he also has to think about plants.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Inside the airfield, pavement alternates with patches of grass, kept short to discourage rodents or insects that attract birds looking for food.</s>
    <s id="8:2">The topsoil is low in nutrition, to prevent grass from growing tall in the first place.</s>
    <s id="8:3">And the grass seeds themselves were chosen because they contain a fungus whose taste drives away waterfowl.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Around the airfield is a buffer zone of 2,646 acres.</s>
    <s id="9:2">Plants with berries, nuts and seeds that attract birds are kept to a minimum.</s>
    <s id="9:3">Instead, Sea-Tac plants shrubs with dense cover that discourages nesting.</s>
    <s id="9:4">Goats were brought in to mow down the especially pervasive blackberries in 2008, but they were a little too good at their job;</s>
    <s id="9:5">they ate all the desirable plants, too.</s>
    <s id="9:6">Now the landscaping is done by humans.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">Sea-Tac was the first airport to hire a wildlife biologist, in the 1970s.</s>
    <s id="10:2">Only a handful of airports across the country have wildlife biologists on staff, though most contract such positions out to the U.S. Department of Agriculture's Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">"Sea-Tac has one of the longest histories of wildlife management," said Ed Herricks, a professor emeritus in civil engineering at the University of Illinois.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Herricks leads a pilot project using radar to detect birds at a few airports including Sea-Tac, chosen in part because of its detailed wildlife-management records.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Nationally, airports are ramping up their efforts against bird strikes.</s>
    <s id="12:2">The number of damaging bird strikes has decreased in recent decades, while wildlife populations and the number of aircraft have increased.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Osmek began his career in marine mammal conservation at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Seattle.</s>
    <s id="13:2">He then moved to New York, where he worked on bird strikes at several airports, and came back 13 years ago to work for the Port of Seattle, which oversees Sea-Tac in addition to the harbor.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">"We got into this because we love animals," he said.</s>
    <s id="14:2">"Here you're trying to mitigate bird-strike hazards, and so much can be done with conservation."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Even the airport's artificial structures plug into a larger natural ecosystem.</s>
    <s id="15:2">Take the stormwater-detention ponds.</s>
    <s id="15:3">To keep away waterfowl like Canada geese, which are large and like to flock, the ponds are covered in nets and lined with black plastic to prevent plants that attract birds.</s>
    <s id="15:4">This strategy has driven waterfowl away from the ponds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">As unnatural as all this plastic is, these ponds have a conservation role.</s>
    <s id="16:2">Because of all the asphalt around the airport, rainwater runoff can overwhelm salmon creeks nearby, so the water is drained into these pools instead.</s>
    <s id="16:3">In the summer, the ponds can augment low water flow.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Airports, like any habitat, are subject to the whims of nature.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Two years ago, the number of bird strikes at Sea-Tac was especially high;</s>
    <s id="17:3">the 121 reported incidents were nearly twice the usual number.</s>
    <s id="17:4">The culprit?</s>
    <s id="17:5">Voles, small mammals resembling mice, which had proliferated during an especially wet spring and attracted birds of prey.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Osmek and his team trapped and relocated more than 100 birds in 2011;</s>
    <s id="18:2">this year, which has been drier, they've relocated 40 so far.</s>
    <s id="18:3">The birds are tagged and taken to northern Washington on Bellair's airport shuttles, and they choose to stay in those skies.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">The most interesting part of the traps for birds of prey may be their bait: pigeons culled from the flock terrorizing the airport's parking garages.</s>
    <s id="19:2">A pair of pigeons both spectacularly lucky and unlucky are cooped in the trap's bottom portion.</s>
    <s id="19:3">They're fed and domesticated — sometimes they even lay eggs, according to Osmek.</s>
    <s id="19:4">But they have to regularly endure hawks swooping down and almost eating them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Invasive bird species, like European starlings, are euthanized rather than relocated.</s>
    <s id="20:2">Osmek estimates they take out a couple thousand starlings every year, and their bodies are given to the Burke Museum, which no longer has to buy birds for students to dissect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">Since live trapping and other initiatives began in 2000, Osmek says, they've seen a big decrease in the starling population.</s>
    <s id="21:2">At the same time, the airport's surrounding area is now home to more songbirds, which do not flock.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">Sea-Tac is also the first airport with an avian radar system, started as a pilot program to validate using radar to detect birds.</s>
    <s id="22:2">Since it was installed in 2007, the system has been refined.</s>
    <s id="22:3">At first, airport duty managers would respond any time a single bird showed up on the radar, but by the time they got to the site in their trucks, the bird would be gone.</s>
    <s id="22:4">Now they know to look only for flocks, which are dispersed with fireworks-type "screamers and bangers."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">Ultimately, there's no way for an airport to be perfectly friendly to the environment.</s>
    <s id="23:2">It's humans who are encroaching on the domain of wildlife.</s>
    <s id="23:3">Instead of fighting nature with more concrete and asphalt, which invariably leads to unintended consequences, humans can play by nature's rules, too.</s>
    <s id="23:4">And that's why even airports need wildlife biologists.</s>
  </p>
</text>
