<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">LONDON — New government documents suggest that spy agencies can collect personal information from smartphones across the globe.</s>
    <s id="1:2">They get the information when people play games or use apps on their phones.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">The documents were leaked by Edward Snowden.</s>
    <s id="2:2">He used to do work for the National Security Agency (NSA), a U.S. spy agency.</s>
    <s id="2:3">These aren't the first documents he's leaked.</s>
    <s id="2:4">Over the past several months he's released other documents and given them to a newspaper.</s>
    <s id="2:5">The documents show how the NSA watches Americans' phone calls and emails.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">The newest documents were published Monday by The New York Times.</s>
    <s id="3:2">The British newspaper the Guardian and ProPublica also published the documents.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Apps are common on the world's roughly 1 billion smartphones.</s>
    <s id="4:2">People download map apps, games, and social networking apps like Facebook.</s>
    <s id="4:3">The leaked documents suggest that America's NSA and Britain's GCHQ spy agency have worked together to gain information from the apps.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">## Leak About "Leaky" Apps</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">Some apps are considered "leaky."</s>
    <s id="6:2">The apps can feed huge amounts of personal information to the spy agencies.</s>
    <s id="6:3">A person's location can be found.</s>
    <s id="6:4">Even details such as a person's political or romantic interests can be discovered.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">The size of the program isn't known.</s>
    <s id="7:2">Yet, the reports suggest that U.S. and British intelligence can easily collect information from apps.</s>
    <s id="7:3">Two of the biggest apps mentioned in reports are "Angry Birds" and Google Maps.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">A 2008 document from the GCHQ describes the spying program.</s>
    <s id="8:2">It says that the program "effectively means that anyone using Google Maps on a smartphone is working in support of a GCHQ system."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">The NSA did not directly comment on the reports.</s>
    <s id="9:2">The NSA says that it is not interested in "the smartphone or social media communications of everyday Americans."</s>
    <s id="9:3">The agency says it collects "only those communications that we are authorized by law to collect."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">The agency says that it monitors phones for good reason.</s>
    <s id="10:2">Often, they are used in planning terrorist activities like bombings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">GCHQ said it does not comment on spying.</s>
    <s id="11:2">It insisted, however, that all of its activity was legal and "necessary."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">It's been known for a while that spy groups are interested in cellphones and the networks they use.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Several of Snowden's previous leaks said as much.</s>
    <s id="12:3">The interest in apps, however, is new.</s>
    <s id="12:4">It shows how even harmless-looking pieces of software can be used for spying.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">## Many Monitored Sites Shown</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">"Angry Birds" was one of the most eye-catching examples.</s>
    <s id="14:2">The addictive game has been downloaded more than 1.7 billion times worldwide.</s>
    <s id="14:3">The game lets players fling birds at pigs to destroy them.</s>
    <s id="14:4">The Times and ProPublica said a 2012 British spy report laid out how to gather "Angry Bird" users' information from phones.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Another document published to the Web was a 14-page-long NSA slideshow.</s>
    <s id="15:2">It listed a host of other apps.</s>
    <s id="15:3">Ones made by Facebook, photo sharing site Flickr, and the film app Flixster were being monitored.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">It wasn't clear precisely what information can be collected.</s>
    <s id="16:2">And from which apps.</s>
    <s id="16:3">One of the slides gave the example of a user who uploaded a photo using a social media app.</s>
    <s id="16:4">A phone's settings, where it connected to, and which websites it had visited could be looked at.</s>
    <s id="16:5">Also, which documents it had downloaded and who its users' friends were could all be found.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Google did not immediately comment on the reports.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Neither did Rovio Entertainment, the maker of "Angry Birds."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">The Times briefly posted a secret U.S. document on the smartphone spying to the Web Monday.</s>
    <s id="18:2">It contained material that appeared to publish the name of an NSA employee.</s>
    <s id="18:3">Computer experts said they were able to discover the name of the employee.</s>
    <s id="18:4">They also picked out the name of a Middle Eastern terror group the NSA was targeting.</s>
    <s id="18:5">Details about the types of computer files the NSA considered useful were also found.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Snowden began leaking documents in June.</s>
    <s id="19:2">His supporters have claimed they have been careful not to release the names of any spies.</s>
    <s id="19:3">They claim to have kept quiet any details that could put ongoing spying at risk.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">A Times spokeswoman said the information had been posted by error.</s>
    <s id="20:2">The material has since been removed.</s>
  </p>
</text>
