<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">MALAM JABBA, Pakistan — Boys in worn-out coats zip down the powdery slope.</s>
    <s id="1:2">They wear homemade pine skis.</s>
    <s id="1:3">They have no ski boots–just galoshes nailed to the planks.</s>
    <s id="1:4">Bamboo sticks work as poles.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Nearby, jobless men climb a snowy ridge.</s>
    <s id="2:2">They are looking for scrap metal.</s>
    <s id="2:3">This is Malam Jabba.</s>
    <s id="2:4">It was once the country's only ski resort.</s>
    <s id="2:5">Now it is strewn with rubble.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">## Taliban Terror</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Malam Jabba is in the Swat Valley.</s>
    <s id="4:2">In 2008 the Taliban took control of the valley.</s>
    <s id="4:3">Taliban fighters believe in an extreme form of Islam.</s>
    <s id="4:4">They terrorized the people of Swat.</s>
    <s id="4:5">Anyone who opposed them was killed.</s>
    <s id="4:6">They set schools on fire.</s>
    <s id="4:7">Girls were banned from classes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">The fighters said skiing was against Islam, their religion.</s>
    <s id="5:2">So they set fire to the resort's hotel.</s>
    <s id="5:3">They broke the chairlift and the snow-making machine.</s>
    <s id="5:4">The ski rental shops were destroyed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">In 2009 the army beat back the Taliban.</s>
    <s id="6:2">The government now controls the valley.</s>
    <s id="6:3">But Malam Jabba remains ruined.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">## Still Waiting For Help</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">"The government has been telling us for years that they're going to rebuild the hotel, and it never happens," said Sabz Ali.</s>
    <s id="8:2">The 18-year-old climbs the slope carrying his skis.</s>
    <s id="8:3">His family owns a small hotel nearby.</s>
    <s id="8:4">It only earns about $20 a month.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">"The [big] hotel is the main thing," Ali says.</s>
    <s id="9:2">"If they build it, people will come."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">## Heartbreak Hotel</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Thousands of people used to come to the resort each day.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Now, the number is usually in the dozens.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">The hotel was a white, modern building.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Inside was a rich-looking lobby.</s>
    <s id="12:3">Guests skated on the ice rink.</s>
    <s id="12:4">The souvenir shop sold local Swat honey.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">"It was a beautiful, huge hotel, and it was always full," Ali said.</s>
    <s id="13:2">He left Swat while the army was fighting the Taliban.</s>
    <s id="13:3">He returned four months later to find the hotel destroyed.</s>
    <s id="13:4">"When I saw it, my heart sank.</s>
    <s id="13:5">It was so beautiful, but it also meant we had jobs."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">## Tourists Stay Away</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">The army has bases and checkpoints to keep out the Taliban.</s>
    <s id="15:2">Still, tourism is not what it used to be.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">About 50,000 tourists come per year, said Zahid Khan.</s>
    <s id="16:2">He speaks for the hotel owners in the valley.</s>
    <s id="16:3">Before the Taliban came there were 300,000 visitors a year, he said.</s>
    <s id="16:4">Fewer visitors means less money for everyone.</s>
    <s id="16:5">Hotel workers, cooks, taxi drivers and handicraft makers are all suffering, Khan explained.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">The government is not doing enough to help tourism in Swat, Khan said.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Top officials ignore him when he asks for meetings and money.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">## More Bad Luck for Swat</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Making matters worse, the region was flooded in 2010.</s>
    <s id="19:2">More than 120 hotels in Swat were damaged or destroyed.</s>
    <s id="19:3">Only 20 have been rebuilt.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">The government said it will oversee the rebuilding of the hotel at Malam Jabba.</s>
    <s id="20:2">Officials say the construction should start this summer.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">People in Swat say they've heard such promises before.</s>
    <s id="21:2">Meanwhile, they are just scraping out a living.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">## Skiing Against All Odds</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">The resort still brings some joy to residents.</s>
    <s id="23:2">They fell in love with skiing long ago.</s>
    <s id="23:3">Besides, there's nothing else to do in Malam Jabba but ski.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">A few dozen people spent hours doing jumps on the mountain.</s>
    <s id="24:2">One skier in an overcoat and sunglasses whizzed down without poles.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">"It's such a beautiful sport that I can't help but ski every day," said Saeed Alam, 22.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">"God has given us this beautiful place and the government doesn't do anything with it," Alam said.</s>
    <s id="26:2">"It's just so disappointing."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">He pushed off down the slope.</s>
    <s id="27:2">On the back of his jacket were the words "Ski and Smile in Swat!"</s>
  </p>
</text>
