<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">ISTANBUL — Violence continued between police and protesters this week in Turkey.</s>
    <s id="1:2">The trouble started when young people gathered to try to stop the government from tearing down a park.</s>
    <s id="1:3">The police sprayed tear gas to make them flee.</s>
    <s id="1:4">About 10,000 people were in the crowd.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Four people have been killed since the protests started on May 28.</s>
    <s id="2:2">Doctors believe that 5,000 people have been injured.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">## City On Two Continents</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">About 13.9 million people live in Istanbul.</s>
    <s id="4:2">It is one of the largest cities in the world.</s>
    <s id="4:3">It also spreads over two continents.</s>
    <s id="4:4">One half of Istanbul lies in Europe, while the other half sits in Asia.</s>
    <s id="4:5">The city is connected by bridges across one of the busiest waterways on the planet, the Bosporus Strait.</s>
    <s id="4:6">Istanbul is an important city for trade.</s>
    <s id="4:7">Turkey is also one of the United States' closest friends in the region.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">Turkey is larger than the state of Texas.</s>
    <s id="5:2">Istanbul is a very modern city, but other parts of Turkey are less developed.</s>
    <s id="5:3">Around 99 percent of Turks have a Muslim background.</s>
    <s id="5:4">However, religion and politics are supposed to remain separate, just as they are in the U.S.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">Turkey's leader is Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan.</s>
    <s id="6:2">Some people feel that Erdogan has tried to force religious laws onto the people.</s>
    <s id="6:3">This is just one reason for the protests against him.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">## Pulling Down A Park For A Shopping Mall</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">The first protests were over a very popular park.</s>
    <s id="8:2">There are plans to replace Gezi Park with a shopping center.</s>
    <s id="8:3">The park is one of the few green spaces for the people of Istanbul.</s>
    <s id="8:4">One protester asked:"What if they tried to demolish Central Park in New York to build a mall?</s>
    <s id="8:5">That's happening here."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Riot police forcefully removed the first protest.</s>
    <s id="9:2">After that, the demonstrations grew much bigger.</s>
    <s id="9:3">The protests are now against the police and the government.</s>
    <s id="9:4">The people protesting are both young and old.</s>
    <s id="9:5">They have lots of different kinds of jobs.</s>
    <s id="9:6">Teachers, doctors, lawyers, office workers and students are all protesting together.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">## Violent Removal</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">On Tuesday, riot police once again removed people from the park.</s>
    <s id="11:2">They used tear gas, water cannons and armored cars.</s>
    <s id="11:3">There were reports that several hundred protesters were injured.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">Several ambulances were seen at the scene.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Online videos showed people panicking as they breathed in the tear gas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">## Secret Police Starting A Fight?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">During the removal, some people threw firebombs at the police.</s>
    <s id="14:2">The protesters said they had never seen these people before.</s>
    <s id="14:3">Some reported seeing the mysterious bombers holding walkie-talkies.</s>
    <s id="14:4">Some believe that they were secret policemen who were sent to the park to start a fight.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Police also stormed a courthouse after protests against Erdogan there.</s>
    <s id="15:2">At least 44 lawyers were arrested.</s>
    <s id="15:3">One lawyer said there were "terrible scenes."</s>
    <s id="15:4">Thousands of lawyers came onto the streets to protest about this on Wednesday.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">Prime Minister Erdogan defended the use of police force against the protesters.</s>
    <s id="16:2">He said the police officers had done a good job.</s>
    <s id="16:3">He accused the protesters of committing crimes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">## "What Should We Have Done?"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">Erdogan promised to "pursue" the protesters who he described as "terrorists."</s>
    <s id="18:2">"No one will escape," he also threatened.</s>
    <s id="18:3">"What should we have done?" </s>
    <s id="18:3">the prime minister asked.</s>
    <s id="18:5">"Kneeled down in front of these people and asked them to please remove their banners?"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Erdogan believes the protests were organized by a foreign country to damage Turkey.</s>
    <s id="19:2">There might be a public vote to decide on the future of the park.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">The U.N. and U.S. government told Turkey to respect the protesters' rights.</s>
    <s id="20:2">Caitlin Hayden is a spokeswoman for the U.S. National Security Council.</s>
    <s id="20:3">Hayden said that she is "concerned by any attempts to punish" people for "exercising their right to free speech."</s>
    <s id="20:4">U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-Moon called for the government and the protesters to talk to each other to resolve the dispute.</s>
  </p>
</text>
