<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">ISTANBUL — The violent battles that have been raging between police and anti-government protesters in Turkey since May 28 continued this week.</s>
    <s id="1:2">On Tuesday, police officers fired tear gas at a group of about 10,000 people who had rallied in Istanbul's Taksim Square.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Three protesters and one police officer have been killed since the clashes began.</s>
    <s id="2:2">The Turkish Medical Association believes that nearly 5,000 people have been injured.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">The demonstrations are putting Turkey and its allies and neighbors on edge.</s>
    <s id="3:2">The Turkish capital, Istanbul, is home to 13.9 million residents and is one of the largest cities in the world.</s>
    <s id="3:3">It also provides a vital link between two continents, as one half of Istanbul sits in Europe while the other half lies in Asia.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">## City On Two Continents</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">The city (and continents) are divided by the Bosphorus Strait.</s>
    <s id="5:2">The waterway is one of the busiest on the planet, making Istanbul a major player in global trade, transportation and communication.</s>
    <s id="5:3">Turkey is also a strong ally to the U.S. and supporter in the war on terror.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">Turkey is larger than the state of Texas, and has borders with Greece in the west and Iran in the east.</s>
    <s id="6:2">While Istanbul is a very modern and Westernized city, much of the rest of the country is less developed and more conservative.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">Around 99 percent of Turks have a Muslim background.</s>
    <s id="7:2">But since 1928 Turkey has been a secular country, where religion is officially separated from the running of government.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Some people feel that the current leader of the government, Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdogan, has recently tried to impose religious laws on this secular society.</s>
    <s id="8:2">Concern that religion is influencing politics is just one of the reasons for the continuing demonstrations in Istanbul.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">## Pulling Down A Park For A Shopping Mall</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">The protests started as a demonstration against demolishing a park and building a shopping center in its place.</s>
    <s id="10:2">Gezi Park is the last piece of green land left in the center of the huge city.</s>
    <s id="10:3">The park is next door to the famous Taksim Square and has been a favorite place for many Turkish people for generations.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">As one of the signs at the first rally said: "What if they tried to demolish Central Park in New York to build a mall?</s>
    <s id="11:2">That's happening here."</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">When the environmental protest was violently evicted from the park by riot police with water cannons and tear gas, the movement mushroomed in size.</s>
    <s id="12:2">The demonstrations are now against police brutality, Prime Minister Erdogan's conservative policies, and the way his government is trying to control the population.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">The demonstrators are both young and old, and from all walks of life.</s>
    <s id="13:2">Teachers, lawyers, office workers and students are all protesting together against their government.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">## Violent Removal</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">Just after dawn on Tuesday morning, riot police once again used tear gas, water cannons and armored vehicles to forcibly clear demonstrators from Taksim Square.</s>
    <s id="15:2">The protesters have now been camped out in the square for more than a week.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">After the violence, government reports suggested there had been just a few injuries, while a doctors' association said that several hundred people were injured.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Many ambulances were seen at the scene.</s>
    <s id="17:2">Videos released online showed protesters panicking and coughing as they inhaled the irritant gas, before helping those who needed to be carried after the police raid.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">## Secret Police Starting A Fight?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">The Taksim Square protests had been mostly peaceful and non-violent.</s>
    <s id="19:2">But TV images from Tuesday showed people throwing Molotov cocktails at police.</s>
    <s id="19:3">Protesters said on Twitter that those attacking the police had not been seen among the demonstrators up until that point.</s>
    <s id="19:4">Other pictures appeared to show the firebomb throwers holding walkie-talkies.</s>
    <s id="19:5">This fueled speculation that these mysterious people were government agents or undercover police sent in to deliberately provoke a fight, and make the protesters look bad.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Police also stormed Istanbul's central court after lawyers held an anti-Erdogan protest there.</s>
    <s id="20:2">At least 44 demonstrating lawyers were taken away.</s>
    <s id="20:3">The Turkish lawyers' association protested the arrests, arguing that its members had simply been demanding an investigation into alleged police brutality during stand-offs between police and protesters.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">"Turkish police have fired their tear gas guns directly at people during the demonstrations of the last days.</s>
    <s id="21:2">They have used it like a projectile weapon.</s>
    <s id="21:3">That's why there are so many severe injuries," association president Metin Feyzioglu told reporters.</s>
    <s id="21:4">He said the lawyers were simply trying to make prosecutors aware of this fact, but were arrested instead.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">"There were terrible scenes," Feyzioglu added.</s>
    <s id="22:2">The next day, thousands of lawyers wearing black robes left their courthouses to support their colleagues and protest their treatment.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">Prime Minister Erdogan defended the latest use of police force against the Istanbul protests.</s>
    <s id="23:2">In a speech to members of his party, he paid tribute to the police leadership and accused the demonstrators of widespread vandalism during the occupation of the square and park.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">## "What Should We Have Done?"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">Erdogan said he wouldn't just "end these protests," but also promised to "pursue" the demonstrators who he described as "provocateurs and terrorists."</s>
    <s id="25:2">No one will escape, he also threatened.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">"What should we have done?"</s>
    <s id="26:2">the prime minister asked in the speech.</s>
    <s id="26:3">"Kneeled down in front of these people and asked them to please remove their banners?"</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">Erdogan called the demonstrations a foreign-aided attempt to force Turkey economically to its knees and intimidate people who want to invest in his country.</s>
    <s id="27:2">On Wednesday, another member of Erdogan's government said that Turkey might hold a referendum to decide on the future of Gezi Park.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">The U.N. and U.S. government urged the Turkish authorities to respect protesters' right to freedom of assembly.</s>
    <s id="28:2">"We are concerned by any attempts to punish individuals for exercising their right to free speech," U.S. National Security Council spokeswoman Caitlin Hayden said.</s>
    <s id="28:3">U.N. Secretary-General Ban Ki-Moon stressed the right to freedom of assembly and called for conversation between the opposing sides to resolve the protests.</s>
  </p>
</text>
